Finding Aid for E. O. Haven pamphlets and reprints
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
E. O. Haven pamphlets and reprints 1838-1881
Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881.
[723] DA 2; H385; P186
President of the University of Michigan, 1863-1881. Articles and speeches on topics in higher education and religion.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a variety of sources.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Erastus O. Haven (1820-1881) served as the second president of the University, 1863-1869. Haven was a minister and leader of the Methodist Episcopal Church during a vigorous period of its growth and development. The child of a Methodist minister and farmer, he was born in Boston and spent most of his childhood in Massachusetts. Upon graduating from Wesleyan University, Haven established a life-long pattern of combining the ministry with teaching. This eventually led him to assume the presidencies of the University of Michigan and Northwestern University as well as the chancellorship of Syracuse University. Haven was deeply interested in educational issues affecting students at all levels and in helping to develop a strong Methodist presence among institutions of higher learning. His presidency at the University of Michigan, along with an earlier four-year stint there as a Latin professor, forced him to deal with the specific problems of a secular state university. Among the topics he discusses during the Michigan years are hazing, secret societies, fiscal issues and institutional administration. In midlife, Haven left his initial position at Michigan to become editor of Zion's Herald, a Methodist newspaper that gave him a voice in the Church's major controversies over slavery, church polity, and temperance. Later, he resigned the presidency of Northwestern University to become Secretary of the Board of Education for the Methodist Episcopal Church. Haven also served two terms in the Massachusetts Senate and was residing as a bishop in San Francisco when he died.
The Haven pamphlets and reprints collection consists of articles and texts of speeches by Haven on a variety of topics higher education and religion and public affairs.
Subjects:
Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881; University of Michigan--History.; Universities and colleges -- Michigan -- Religion.; Methodism.
- Pamphlet and reprints.
  - The true object of a seminary. A farewell address, delivered at Amenia seminary, 1848 (Box 1)
  - Anniversary address before the union missionary society of inquiry, in the University of Michigan, 1853
  - Common schools unsectarian. A discourse delivered in the M. E. Church at Ann Arbor, Mich., 1853
  - Increased mental activity of the age; its causes and demands, 1854
  - Speech on the Hoosac tunnel bill. l862
  - Report of the school committee of Malden, Mass., 1862
  - Annual message to the third moot congress of the law department of the University of Michigan., 1863
  - Report of the school committee of Malden, Mass., 1863
  - Senate....No. l08, 1863
  - Should the nation be thankful?, 1863
  - Universities in America. An inaugural address delivered in Ann Arbor, Michigan., 1863
  - The relation of the medical profession to science, 1864
  - Annual message to the fourth moot congress of the law department, 1864
  - Memorial proceedings in honor of the lamented president of the United States, Abraham Lincoln, 1865
  - The legal profession in America, 1866
  - Methodism, and the sources of its power, 1866
  - Duties of the medical profession, 1867
  - Public education and religion, 1867
  - Responsibility of finite beings, 1867
  - Science and religion, 1867
  - The medical profession, 1869
  - The function of Universities, 1881
  - Freedom of thought lecture in response to Robert G. Ingersoll, undated